Civil Rights History Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2: Interviews
  - William Saunders oral history interview conducted by Kieran Walsh Taylor in Charleston, South Carolina, June 9, 2011
    - Moving Images, 4 video files of 4 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (84 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0027_mv01-04
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (49 pages); afc2010039_crhp0027_saunders_transcript (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Esther M. A. Terry oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Greensboro, North Carolina, July 6, 2011
    Biographical History: Esther M. A. Terry was born in 1939 in Wise, North Carolina, as one of twelve siblings. She attended Bennett College, the University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill, and the University of Massachusetts Amherst. She worked as professor and academic administrator.
    Summary: Esther M. A. Terry remembers growing up in Wise, North Carolina, and attending Bennett College. She recalls planning the Greensboro Woolworth's sit-in with students from the Agricultural and Technical College of North Carolina (later North Carolina A&T University), being arrested for her participation, and the support of the Bennett College President, Dr. Willa Player. She also discusses attending the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill for her master's degree, and founding the African American Studies program at the University of Massachusetts (Amherst campus), where she earned her PhD and taught for many years.
    - Moving Images, 6 video files of 6 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (92 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0028_mv01-06
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (37 pages); afc2010039_crhp0028_terry_transcript (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Evans Derrell Hopkins oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Richmond, Virginia, July 7, 2011
    Biographical History: Evans Hopkins was born in 1954 in Danville, Virginia, married Ruth Hopkins, and had one son. He attended R.J. Reynolds High School and Winston-Salem State University. He joined the Black Panther Party and worked as a writer. Hopkins is the author of the book, Life After Life: A Story of Rage and Redemption.
    Summary: Evans Hopkins recalls growing up in Danville, Virginia, and participating in efforts to desegregate public schools and the library. He remembers joining the Black Panther Party in Winston-Salem, North Carolina, and Oakland, California, and working on Bobby Seale's campaign for Mayor of Oakland. He also discusses his imprisonment for car theft and the high rate of incarceration among African American men.
    - Moving Images, 9 video files of 9 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (118 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0029_mv01-09
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (45 pages); afc2010039_crhp0029_hopkins_transcript (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Courtland Cox oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Washington, D.C., July 8, 2011
    Biographical History: Courtland Cox was born in 1941 in Harlem, New York. He attended Howard University and worked in government and business in Washington, D. C. Cox was a civil rights activist and a founder of the group that became the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC).
    Summary: Courtland Cox recalls growing up in Trinidad and New York City, and attending Howard University. He remembers organizing student protests in Washington, D. C., with the Nonviolent Action Group, which later merged with other groups to become the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). He also discusses the March on Washington, the Democratic National Convention in Atlantic City, changes in SNCC, and attending the Sixth Pan-African Congress.
    - Moving Images, 9 video files of 9 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (104 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0030_mv01-09
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (46 pages); afc2010039_crhp0030_cox_transcript (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Simeon Booker and Moses James Newson oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Washington, D.C., July 13, 2011
    Biographical History: Simeon Booker was born in 1918 in Baltimore, Maryland. He attended Virginia Union University and became a the first African American journalist at the Washington Post. He covered the trial of Emmett Till's murder and the civil rights movement for Jet and Ebony.
    Biographical History: Moses J. Newson was born in 1927 in Fruitland Park, Florida, married Lucille Wallace in 1948, and had four children. He attended Storer College and Lincoln University, and worked as a journalist covering the civil rights movement for the Memphis Tri-State Defender and the Baltimore Afro-American.
    Summary: Simeon Booker and Moses Newson recall their early careers in journalism at several African American newspapers. Newson remembers covering school desegregation cases in Clinton, Tennessee and Hoxie, Arkansas, for the Memphis Tri-State Defender. Booker discusses covering the Emmett Till murder and the integration of Little Rock High School for Jet. They both remember covering the Freedom Rides and the March on Washington.
    - Moving Images, 7 video files of 7 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (92 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0031_mv01-07
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (38 pages); afc2010039_crhp0031_bookerandnewson_transcript (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Freeman A. Hrabowski oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Baltimore, Maryland, August 14, 2011
    Biographical History: Freeman Hrabowski was born in 1950 in Birmingham, Alabama, married Jacqueline Coleman, and had one son. He attended Hampton Institute and the University of Illinois-Urbana Champaign, and was the president of the University of Maryland, Baltimore County. He participated in the 1963 Children's Crusade in Birmingham.
    Summary: Freeman A. Hrabowski recalls growing up in Birmingham, Alabama, and attending the Sixth Avenue Baptist Church. He remembers being arrested for marching in the Birmingham Children's Crusade in 1963, and remembers the bombing of the 16th Street Baptist Church. He also discusses attending Hampton University and later starting the Meyerhoff Scholars Program for African American men studying math and science.
    - Moving Images, 6 video files of 6 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (78 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0032_mv01-06
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (45 pages); afc2010039_crhp0032_hrabowski_transcript (Box-folder 2/14)
  - John Elliott Churchville oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, July 15, 2011
    Biographical History: John Churchville was born in 1941 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. He attended Antioch University, Rutgers School of Law, and Canterbury University, and worked as lawyer, businessperson, educator and community organizer. He was a civil rights activist and member of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC).
    Summary: John Churchville recalls growing up in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, his mother's career as a music teacher, moving to New York, and converting to Islam. He remembers joining the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), registering voters in Americus, Georgia, and in Mississippi. He discusses moving back to Philadelphia, converting to Christianity, and founding the Freedom Library and Black People's Unity Movement.
    - Moving Images, 7 video files of 7 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (153 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0033_mv01-07
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (73 pages); afc2010039_crhp0033_churchville_transcript (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Jack Greenberg oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in New York, New York, July 18, 2011
    Biographical History: Jack Greenberg was born in 1924 in Brooklyn, New York. He attended Columbia University and worked as a staff attorney and Director-Counsel for the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund and as a law professor. He is the author of Crusaders in the Courts: How a Dedicated Band of Lawyers Fought for the Civil Rights Revolution (2004).
    Summary: Jack Greenberg remembers attending Columbia University Law School, working for the NAACP Legal Defense and Education Fund, and arguing the Brown v. Board of Education case. He discusses working on many other civil rights cases, such as Coke v. City of Atlanta, Swann v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg Board of Education, and Griggs v. Duke Power.
    - Moving Images, 9 video files of 9 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (47 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0034_mv01-09
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (22 pages); afc2010039_crhp0034_greenberg_transcript (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Gloria Hayes Richardson oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in New York, New York, July 19, 2011
    Biographical History: Gloria Hayes Richardson was born in 1922 in Baltimore, Maryland, married Henry Richardson in 1945 and Frank Dandridge in 1964, and had two children. She attended Howard University and worked as a city contract manager and program officer. She was a civil rights activist in Cambridge, Maryland, and a member of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC).
    Summary: Gloria Richardson recalls growing up in Cambridge, Maryland, attending Howard University, and joining Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) with her daughter, Donna, after returning to Cambridge and running her father's drug store. She recalls traveling to the South with her family to assist SNCC with voter registration, organizing the Cambridge Nonviolent Action Committee, assisting E. Franklin Frazier with research on African Americans, and marching in a protest where the police used cyanogen gas. She also discusses attending the March on Washington, her involvement with the Nation of Islam, and meeting Malcolm X.
    - Moving Images, 5 video files of 5 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (92 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0035_mv01-05
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (49 pages); afc2010039_crhp0035_richardson_transcript (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Alfred Moldovan oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in New York, New York, July 19, 2011
    Biographical History: Alfred Moldovan was born in 1921 the Bronx, New York, married Jean Moldovan, and had two children. He attended City College and Chicago Medical School and worked as a doctor and member of the Medical Committee for Human Rights.
    Summary: Alfred Moldovan remembers growing up in the Bronx and the influence of his parents, who were Jewish Hungarian immigrants. He recalls serving in the air force as a radio repairman during World War II and later attending medical school. He discusses founding the Medical Committee for Human Rights and traveling to the South to assist injured civil rights activists at events such as the Selma to Montgomery March.
    - Moving Images, 4 video files of 4 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (59 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0036_mv01-04
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (31 pages); afc2010039_crhp0036_moldovan_transcript (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Junius W. Williams oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Newark, New Jersey, July 20, 2011
    Biographical History: Junius Williams was born in 1943 in Suffolk, Virginia, married Antoinette Ellis, and had four children. He attended Amherst College and Yale University, and worked as an attorney, musician, and educator. He was a civil rights activist and member of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC).
    Summary: Junius Williams recalls growing up in Richmond, Virginia, attending Amherst College, and joining the student group Students for Racial Equality. He remembers attending the March on Washington, organizing a civil rights conference at Mount Holyoke, and joining the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). He also discusses traveling with other students to the Selma to Montgomery March, being arrested at the march with Worth Long, working as a community organizer with the Newark Community Union Project, and witnessing the riots in Newark, New Jersey, in 1967.
    - Moving Images, 9 video files of 9 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (174 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0037_mv01-09
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (87 pages); afc2010039_crhp0037_williamsj_transcript (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Emmett W. Bassett and Priscilla Tietjen Bassett oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Grahamsville, New York, July 21, 2011
    Biographical History: Emmett W. Bassett was born in 1921 in Henry County, Virginia, attended Tuskegee Institute, University of Massachusetts, and Ohio State University, and worked as a microbiologist. Priscilla Tietjen Bassett was born in 1928 in Plainfield, New Jersey, attended Smith College and Queens College and worked as a librarian. The Bassetts married in 1950, had three children, and were civil rights activists in New York.
    Biographical History: Priscilla Tietjen Bassett was born on May 25, 1928 in Plainfield, New Jersey. She married Emmett Bassett in 1950 and had three children, Mitzi, Jonathan and Lydia. She attended Smith College, AB; Queens College, New York, MLS and worked as a librarian.
    Summary: Priscilla Tietjen Bassett recalls growing up in Plainfield, New Jersey, and attending Smith College, and Emmett W. Bassett remembers growing up in Henry County, Virginia, serving in World War II, and attending Tuskegee Institute, where he assisted George Washington Carver with research. They tell how they met at a protest of a segregated restaurant in Massachusetts, raising money for Emmett Till's mother, their involvement in many civil rights groups in New York, and attending the March on Washington. They also discuss Emmett's career as a professor of dairy science, Priscilla's career as a librarian, and their struggles as an interracial married couple.
    - Moving Images, 10 video files of 10 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (131 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0038_mv01-10
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (71 pages); afc2010039_crhp0038_bassett_transcript (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Pete Seeger oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Beacon, New York, July 22, 2011
    Biographical History: Pete Seeger was born in 1919 in New York, New York, married Toshi-Aline Ota in 1943, and had three children. He attended Harvard University and was a folk singer and civil rights activist.
    Summary: Pete Seeger recalls performing at a concert with Paul Robeson in 1949 in Peekskill, New York, visiting the Highlander Folk School, and the evolution of the song We Shall Overcome. He remembers performing at many civil rights events, including the Selma to Montgomery March. He also discusses his thoughts on Presidents Barack Obama and Rutherford B. Hayes.
    - Moving Images, 4 video files of 4 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (57 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0039_mv01-04
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (25 pages) including draft corrections; afc2010039_crhp0039_seeger_transcript (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Dorothy Foreman Cotton oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Ithaca, New York, July 25, 2011
    Biographical History: Dorothy Cotton was born in 1930 in Goldsboro, North Carolina and married George Junius Cotton in 1955. She attended Shaw University, Virginia State College, and Boston University. She worked as a civil rights worker, leader, and educator.
    Summary: Dorothy Foreman Cotton discusses growing up in rural North Carolina, attending Shaw University and Virginia State College, working as a housekeeper for the president of these colleges, Dr. Robert Prentiss Daniel, and meeting her husband, George Cotton. She discusses attending the Gillfield Baptist Church in Petersburg, Virginia, working with pastor Wyatt T. Walker on organizing civil rights protests and meetings, and meeting Martin Luther King, Jr. She moved to Atlanta to assist Walker in his work with the Southern Christian Leadership Conference, where she became Director of Education for the organization. At the Highlander Folk School, she met Septima Clark and Esau Jenkins and led the Citizenship Education Program. She also discusses the impact of King's assassination on the movement and the philosophy of nonviolence.
    - Moving Images, 8 video files of 8 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (133 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0040_mv01-08
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (66 pages); afc2010039_crhp0040_cotton_transcript (Box-folder 3/8)
  - William G. Anderson oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Detroit, Michigan, July 26, 2011
    Biographical History: William G. Anderson was born in 1927 in Americus, Georgia, married Norma Lee Dixon, and had five children. He attended Fort Valley State College, Atlanta College of Mortuary Science, and Des Moines Still College of Osteopathy, and worked as an osteopath. He was also a civil rights activist in Albany, Georgia.
    Summary: William Anderson recalls growing up in Americus, Georgia, serving in the navy during World War II, and his friendships with Martin Luther King, Jr., and Ralph Abernathy. He remembers opening his osteopath practice in Albany, Georgia, becoming a leader of the Albany Movement, and supporting protesters from the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). He discusses his several arrests with King and Abernathy, appearing on Meet the Press, the closing of all public facilities in Albany, and his later friendship with Sheriff Laurie Pritchett.
    - Moving Images, 6 video files of 6 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (153 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0041_mv01-06
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (56 pages); afc2010039_crhp0041_andersonw_transcript (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Phil Hutchings oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Oakland, California, September 1, 2011
    Biographical History: Phil Hutchings was born in 1942 in Cleveland, Ohio. He attended Howard University and worked in education and non-profit management. He was a civil rights activist and member of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) in Newark, New Jersey.
    Summary: Phil Hutchings recalls growing up in Cleveland, Ohio, his parents' involvement in many civic organizations, and attending Howard University. He remembers joining the Nonviolent Action Group (a precursor to the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC)), protesting at the White Rice Inn in Maryland, and working with the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party. He discusses moving to Newark, New Jersey, to work for SNCC, Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), and the Newark Community Union Project. He also recalls organizing District of Columbia residents for the March on Washington and witnessing the Newark riots in 1967.
    - Moving Images, 9 video files of 9 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (164 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0042_mv01-09
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (90 pages); afc2010039_crhp0042_hutchings_transcript (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Thomas Walter Gaither oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, September 12, 2011
    Biographical History: Thomas Gaither was born in 1938 in Great Falls, South Carolina, married Diane Jenner in 1968 and had two children. He attended Claflin University, Atlanta University, and the University of Iowa. He worked as a construction laborer, civil rights activist, forester, and biology professor at Slippery Rock University.
    Summary: Thomas Gaither recalls growing up in Great Falls, South Carolina, attending Claflin College, and leading the college's National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) chapter. He remembers the student sit-ins in Orangeburg, South Carolina, joining the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), and being arrested for protesting in Hollywood, Florida. He discusses organizing the Freedom Rides, his belief in nonviolence, and earning his PhD in biology at the University of Iowa.
    - Moving Images, 9 video files of 9 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (131 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0043_mv01-09
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (63 pages); afc2010039_crhp0043_gaither_transcript (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Audrey Nell Hamilton and JoeAnn Anderson Ulmer oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Saint Augustine, Florida, September 13, 2011
    Biographical History: Audrey Hamilton grew up in Saint Augustine, Florida, and participated in the Civil Rights Movement.
    Biographical History: JoeAnn Ulmer grew up in Saint Augustine, Florida, and participated in the Civil Rights Movement.
    Summary: Audrey Hamilton and JoeAnn Ulmer recall growing up in St. Augustine, Florida, and participating in sit-ins led by Dr. Robert Hayling at Woolworth's drug store as teenagers. They recall serving a sentence in jail, attending reform school, and meeting Martin Luther King, Jr., and Jackie Robinson.
    - Moving Images, 2 video files of 2 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (66 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0044_mv01-02
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (36 pages); afc2010039_crhp0044_hamiltonandulmer_transcript (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Purcell Maurice Conway oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Saint Augustine, Florida, September 13, 2011
    Biographical History: Purcell Conway was born in 1948 in Saint Augustine, Florida. He participated in the Civil Rights Movement in Saint Augustine and worked as a police officer in New York.
    Summary: Purcell Conway recalls growing up in St. Augustine, Florida, and working many odd jobs. He recalls facing discrimination, participating in demonstrations, and witnessing a riot when attempting to integrate the beach. He also discusses moving to New York City, his career as a police officer, and successfully suing the city for discrimination in promotions.
    - Moving Images, 4 video files of 4 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (77 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0045_mv01-04
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (39 pages); afc2010039_crhp0045_conway_transcript (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Barbara Edna Vickers oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Saint Augustine, Florida, September 13, 2011
    Biographical History: Barbara Vickers was born in 1923 in Saint Augustine, Florida, and attended Excelsior High School. She was a beautician and civil rights activist in Saint Augustine.
    Summary: Barbara Vickers recalls growing up in St. Augustine, Florida, working in a shipyard in New York during World War II, and returning to St. Augustine with her husband. She remembers working as a beautician, working with her neighbor, Dr. Robert Hayling, to organize civil rights protests and participating in kneel-ins in segregated churches. She also discusses raising money to build a monument to the foot soldiers of the Civil Rights Movement in St. Augustine.
    - Moving Images, 4 video files of 4 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (59 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0046_mv01-04
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (31 pages); afc2010039_crhp0046_vickers_transcript (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Gwendolyn Annette Duncan oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Saint Augustine, Florida, September 14, 2011
    Biographical History: Gwendolyn Duncan was born in 1956 in Saint Augustine, Florida, married Richard Allen Duncan in 1976, and had five children. She attended St. John's River College and worked as an educator and in non-profit management. Duncan is President of 40th ACCORD (formally the 40th Anniversary to Commemorate the Civil Rights Demonstrations, Inc.), a non-profit established 2003 to promote awareness of local civil rights movement history.